<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<section xml:id="section-realization">
		<title>Realization of a Weave Pattern</title>

<p><index><main>Minsets</main></index> Given a collection of subsets of some set, their minsets are the atoms which cannot be divided by standard set operations. Minsets hold the key to how the harnesses of a loom should be threaded in order to realize a weave pattern, and to determine whether the pattern can even be realized with a specific loom. </p>

<p>Whether a pattern can be realized is determined by whether each of the distinct horizontal rows of the pattern can be realized. Let <m>r_1,\dots , r_n</m> be those rows. Each row <m>r_i</m> is realized be lifting a set <m>R_i</m> of warp fibers. Give two warp fibers <m>f_1</m> and <m>f_2</m>, if <m>f_1, f_2 \in R_i</m> for some <m>i</m> yet <m>f_1 \in R_j</m> while <m>f_2 \notin R_j</m>, we cannot connect <m>f_1</m> and <m>f_2</m> to the same harness.   If we presume that all warp fibers are connected to exactly one harness, with the set of warp fibers connected to harness <m>i</m> equal to <m>H_i</m>, then the warp fibers lifted to realize a row must be a union of the <m>H_i's</m>. These observations imply that <m>\{H_i\}</m> would be the minsets generated by <m>\{R_j\}</m>.  For each <m>i</m>,

<me>H_i = \bigcap_{j=1}^{n}{\tilde{R}_j}</me> 
where <m>\tilde{R}_j</m> is either <m>R_j</m>  or <m>R_j^c</m>.
</p> 

<!-- 
		<sage>
			 <input>
			 A = matrix(4,5, srange(20))
			 A.rref()
			 </input>
			 <output>
			 [ 1  0 -1 -2 -3]
			 [ 0  1  2  3  4]
			 [ 0  0  0  0  0]
			 [ 0  0  0  0  0]
			 </output>
		</sage>
 -->
 
 

<p>We number the warp threads left to right with the numbers 1 to <m>w</m>, and the harnesses with numbers 0 through <m>n-1</m>.</p>

The simplest weave case is a two harness arrangement where warp thread <m>k</m> is connected to harness k mod 2. If each of two treadles are connected to the two harnesses, and treadles are alternated, the result is a "plain weave."  There are two different lift patterns here. 

Figure here. 


Fundamental question:  given a weave pattern with a certain set of lift patterns and look with a number available harnesses and treadle s, is it possible to realize the pattern with that loom?

  </section>